<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<!-- to update pretext repository, cd mathbook followed by git pull -->

<!-- To process this file do                                                                      -->
<!--                                                                                              -->
<!-- (1) LaTeX/PDF:                                                                               -->
<!--     xsltproc -o worksheets.tex ~/mathbook/xsl/mathbook-latex.xsl worksheets.xml                      -->
<!--     pdflatex worksheets.tex                                                                     -->
<!--     xelatex worksheets.tex                                                                      -->
<!--                                                                                              -->
<!-- (2) HTML:                                                                                -->
<!--         cd dfranz-ju.github.io/math-320                                          -->
<!--     xsltproc ~/mathbook/xsl/pretext-html.xsl worksheets.xml                                 -->
<!--                                                                                              -->
<!--    to update git repository, do                        -->
<!--       git add -x-all  (double hyphen,no x)                                   -->
<!--       git commit -m "<short descriptive comment>"       -->
<!--       git push -u origin master                         -->       
<!-- 														-->
<!--   website is https://dfranz-ju.github.io/Math-320/frontmatter-1.html. -->                                      
                                             



<pretext>
	<docinfo>
		<macros>
			<!-- simple latex macros (\newcommand) go here-->
			
		</macros>
	</docinfo>
	
	
 <book xml:id="Math-320-Guided-Practice">
 <title>Math 320 Guided Practice</title>
 
 <frontmatter>
	 <titlepage>
		 <author>
			 <personname>Dr. Daniel Franz</personname>
			 <institution>Jacksonville University</institution>
		 </author>
		 <date><today /></date>
	 </titlepage>
	 
	 <abstract>
		 This is a collection of Guided Practice assignments for use in Math 320.
	 </abstract>
 
 </frontmatter>
 
 <introduction>
	 <p>
	 	This is a collection of Guided Practice assignments for use in Math 320.
	 </p>
 </introduction>
 
 <chapter xml:id="chapter-systems">
	 <title>Systems of Linear Equations</title>
	 

	 
	 <section xml:id="section-1-1">
		 <title>Guided Practice 1.1: Systems of Linear Equations</title>
		 
		 <introduction>
			 <title>Overview</title>
			 <p>
			 In this section, we begin our study of linear systems of equations, one of the main topics of Linear Algebra. The section starts by collecting some basic terminology and presenting a geometric context for linear systems to help understand their possible solutions. We then introduce matrix notation for linear systems and show its usefulness in solving linear systems with an example which motivates the definition of the <term>elementary row operations</term>. The section concludes with a discussion of <em>consistency</em> and <em>solution uniqueness</em> for linear systems. 
		 </p>
			 
		 <p>
			 <alert>Historical Note:</alert> Systems of linear equations have a long history dating back thousands of years, as described in this note by Viktor Katz from the textbook Linear Algebra, 3rd ed., by Fraleigh and Beauregard:
			 
			 <blockquote>
			 <p>
			 Systems of linear equations are found in ancient Babylonian and Chinese texts dating back well over 2000 years. The problems are generally stated in real-life terms, but it is clear they are artificial and designed simply to train students in mathematical procedures. 
		 </p>
		<p>	 
			 As an example of a Babylonian problem, consider the following, which has been slightly modified from the original found on a clay tablet from about 300 BCE: There are two fields whose total area is 1800 square yards. One produces grain at a rate of <m>\frac{2}{3}</m> bushel per square yard, the other at a rate of <m>\frac{1}{2}</m> bushel per square yard. The total yield of the two fields is 1100 bushels. What is the size of each field? 
		 </p>
		 <p>
			 This problem leads to the system
			 <md>
				 <mrow> x + y \amp = 1800 </mrow>
				 <mrow> \frac{2}{3} x + \frac{1}{2} y \amp = 1100 </mrow>
			 </md>
		 </p>
		 <p>
			 A typical Chinese problem, taken from the Han dynasty text <pubtitle>Nine Chapters of the Mathematical Art</pubtitle> (about 200 BCE), reads as follows: There are three classes of corn, of which three bundles of the first class, two of the second, and one of the third make 39 measures. Two of the first, three of the second, and one of the third make 34 measures. And one of the first, two of the second, and three of the third make 26  measures. How many measures of grain are contained in one bundle of each class? 
		 </p>
		 <p>
			 The system of equations here is 
			 <md>
				 <mrow> 3x+2y+z \amp =39 </mrow>
				 <mrow> 2x + 3y + z \amp = 34</mrow>
				 <mrow> x + 2y + 3z \amp = 26</mrow>
			 </md>
		 </p>
		 
	 </blockquote>
 </p>
		 </introduction>
		 
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-1-BLO">
			 <title>Basic Learning Objectives </title>
		<p>
			 You should be able to perform these tasks with reasonable fluency <em>when you arrive to class</em>.
			 
			 <ul>
				 <li>
				 	Describe the possible solution sets of a linear system of equations.
				 </li>
				 <li>
				 	Translate a linear system into its corresponding coefficient and augmented matrices.
				 </li>
				 <li>
				 	Translate an augmented matrix into a linear system.
				 </li>
				 <li>
				 	Apply elementary row operations to matrices.
				 </li>
			 </ul>
			
		 </p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-1-ALO">
			 <title>Advanced Learning Objectives </title>
		<p>
			In addition to mastering the basic objectives, here are the tasks you should be able to perform <em>after class, with practice</em>:
			 
			 <ul>
				 <li>
				 	Use elementary row operations to determine if a linear system is consistent.
				 </li>
				 <li>
				 	Solve linear systems that have unique solutions using elementary row operations.
				 </li>
			 </ul>
			
		 </p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-1-Resources">
			 <title>Resources</title>
			 <p>
				 <em>Reading</em>: Read Section 1.1 of the textbook, keeping the learning objectives in mind. It's helpful to write down new vocabulary words and notation along with short definitions/examples and to actively work along with the examples on your own paper.
			 </p>
			
			
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-1-Sage">
			 <title>Sage Commands</title>

 			<p>
 				The elementary row operations can be easily applied using Sage. First, we create a matrix that we can apply row operations to using the <c>matrix</c> command. The <c>QQ</c> is telling Sage to treat the entries of the matrix as rational numbers, so that we may divide later. (Evaluate the cell below)
 			</p>
			
 			<sage>
 				<input>
 					A=matrix(QQ, [[5,3,1], [1,4,-2]]); #creates a matrix and names it A
					A #prints the matrix named A
 				</input>
 			</sage>

			
 			<p>
 				To use the <term>Interchange</term> row operation, we use the <c>swap_rows</c> method. Note that Sage always starts counting at 0, so the first row is row 0.
 			</p>	
			
 			<sage>
 				<input>
					A=matrix(QQ, [[5,3,1], [1,4,-2]]);
					A.swap_rows(0,1); #swaps row 0 and row 1
					A
 				</input>
 				<output>
 					[1 4 -2]
 					[5 3 1 ]
 				</output>
 			</sage>
			
			<p>
				Sage keeps track of previous cell evaluations, so we did not need to define A again in the cell above. However, we are changing A with each row operation and if we want to change our mind or try a different row operation, it can be difficult to keep track of the edits. By putting everything in the same cell, we don't have to remember invisible information (which cells were executed in which order). In your own work on CoCalc, you can just keep adding commands to the same cell as opposed to creating new cells with repeated commands.
			</p>
			
 			<p>
 				We now use a <term>Replacement</term> row operation; since this operation adds a multiple of one row to another row, the method name is <c>add_multiple_of_row</c>.
 			</p>
			
 			<sage>
 				<input>
					A=matrix(QQ, [[5,3,1], [1,4,-2]]);
					A.swap_rows(0,1);
					A.add_multiple_of_row(1,0,-5); #adds -5*row 0 to row 1
					A
 				</input>
 			</sage>
			
 			<p>
 				To understand the syntax of the method <c>add_multiple_of_row</c>, read it right to left. In the above example, we added <m>-5\cdot</m> Row 0 to Row 1 (where Row 0 is the first row).
 			</p>
			
 			<p>
 				A <term>Scaling</term> operation will make that second row look nicer. We use the <c>rescale_row</c> method.
 			</p>
			
 			<sage>
 				<input>
					A=matrix(QQ, [[5,3,1], [1,4,-2]]);
					A.swap_rows(0,1);
					A.add_multiple_of_row(1,0,-5);
					A.rescale_row(1, -1/17); #multiplies row 1 by -1/17
					A
 				</input>
 			</sage>
			
 			<p>
 				You should see a 4 as the top middle entry. Try using a Replacement operation in the Sage cell below to change the top middle entry to a 0. (Feel free to use copy and paste!)
 			</p>
			
 			<sage>
 				<input>
					
 				</input>
 			</sage>
			
			
			
 		</subsection>
		 
		
		<exercises>
			<p>
				Complete the following exercises in the GP 1-1 file in CoCalc by 8:00 AM on 8/20/2020. (The questions are already included in the CoCalc file)
			</p>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					A given linear system of equations in three variables has <m>x=4, y=2, z=1</m> and <m>x=-1, y=4, z=2</m> as solutions. How many total solutions does this system have? (Answer in a Markdown cell)
				</statement>
				
			</exercise>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					Create the augmented matrix of the linear system of equations below using the Sage <c>matrix</c> command. Write the command in the code cell below (and execute it).
					<md>
						<mrow> x_2 + 4x_3 \amp = -5</mrow>
						<mrow> x_1 + 3x_2 + 5x_3 \amp = -2</mrow>
						<mrow> 3x_1 + 7x_2 + 7x_3 \amp = 0</mrow>
					</md>
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					Write the linear system of equations corresponding to the augmented matrix below. (Answer in a Markdown cell)
					<me> \begin{bmatrix} 2 \amp -3 \amp -5 \\ -4 \amp 6 \amp 10 \end{bmatrix}</me>
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			

			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					In each part, use a Sage command to apply the given elementary row operation to the matrix <m>B = \begin{bmatrix} 1 \amp 2 \amp 3 \\ 4 \amp 5 \amp 6 \\ 7 \amp 8 \amp 9 \end{bmatrix}</m>. Each answer should be written in a code cell that executes correctly. Note: each row operation should be applied to the initial matrix <m>B</m>; they should not be applied sequentially.
					<ol>
						<li>
							Swap the second and third row of B.
						</li>
						
						<li>
							Multiply the first row of B by 4.
						</li>
						
						<li>
							Add the first row to the third row.
						</li>
					</ol>
					
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					What comments or questions do you have about the content of this assignment? (Answer in a Markdown cell)
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
		</exercises>	
	
	 </section>
	 
	 
	 
	 
	 
	 
	 
	 
	 
	 
	 
	 <section xml:id="section-1-2">
		 <title>Guided Practice 1.2: Row Reduction and Echelon Forms</title>
		 
		 <introduction>
			 <title>Overview</title>
			 <p>
			 This section continues the study of systems of linear equations and their solutions. We refine the methods from Section 1.1 of solving linear systems by introducting the notions of <em>echelon form</em> and <em>reduced echelon form</em> of a matrix. When an augmented matrix is in echelon form, questions about consistency and uniqueness of solutions can be easily answered. When an augmented matrix is in reduced echelon form, we can easliy solve the system (if it is consistent).
		 </p>
			 
		 <p>
			 Examples 2 and 3 illustrate the <em>Row Reduction Algorithm</em>, which we use to reduce a matrix to echelon or reduced echelon form. The section continues by showing how to use reduced echelon form to solve linear systems. Many of the problems and concepts the rest of the semester will involve reducing matrices to echelon or reduced echelon form and analyzing the result; while we will eventually use a single Sage command to accomplish the computational side, we will be interpreting reduced echelon form matrices in different contexts the remainder of the semester. 
		 </p>
		 
		 </introduction>
		 
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-2-BLO">
			 <title>Basic Learning Objectives </title>
		<p>
			 You should be able to perform these tasks with reasonable fluency <em>when you arrive to class</em>.
			 
			 <ul>
				 <li>
				 	Determine if a matrix is in echelon or reduced echelon form (or neither).
				 </li>
				 <li>
				 	Identify pivot positions of a matrix in echelon or reduced echelon form.
				 </li>
				 <li>
				 	Determine the basic and free variables of a linear system.
				 </li>
			 </ul>
			
		 </p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-2-ALO">
			 <title>Advanced Learning Objectives </title>
		<p>
			In addition to mastering the basic objectives, here are the tasks you should be able to perform <em>after class, with practice</em>:
			 
			 <ul>
				 <li>
				 	Determine the solution set type (none, one, or infinite) of a linear system given its augmented matrix in echelon form.
				 </li>
				 <li>
				 	Implement the row reduction algorithm to convert a matrix to echelon or reduced echelon form.
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 Find the general solution of a linear system and express it in parametric form.
				 </li>
			 </ul>
			
		 </p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-2-Resources">
			 <title>Resources</title>
			 <p>
				 <em>Reading</em>: Read Section 1.2 of the textbook, keeping the learning objectives in mind. It's helpful to write down new vocabulary words and notation along with short definitions/examples and to actively work along with the examples on your own paper. Example 3 is the main example of applying the row reduction algorithm. The section ends with a general strategy for solving linear systems.
			 </p>
			 
			 <p>
				 <em>Video</em>: The video below, recorded by me, demonstrates the process of row reducing a matrix into reduced echelon form using Sage commands in CoCalc. I recommend watching it after reading Example 3 in the textbook, then read Example 3 again. 

				 	 <video youtube="GiZxxzEwN-M"/>
				</p> 
			
			
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-2-Sage">
			 <title>Sage Commands</title>

 			<p>
 				The <c>rref</c> method outputs the reduced echelon form of the matrix it is applied to. Note that by Theorem 1 of this section, each matrix has a <em>unique</em> reduced echelon form. This makes this an excellent tool for checking your work, as you can immeditely tell by inspection if you have reduced a matrix correctly. 
			</p>
				
			<p>
				For now, I expect you to continue using elementary row operations when row reducing, using <c>rref</c> only to check your work. Later in the semester, you will be allowed to use <c>rref</c> whenever a problem requires you to row reduce a matrix.
				
			</p>	
				
			<p>
				A couple of examples below show the <c>rref</c> method in action.
			</p>
 			
			
			
			
 			<sage>
 				<input>
 					A=matrix(QQ, [[5,3,1], [1,4,-2]]); #creates a matrix and names it A
					print(A) #prints the matrix named A
					A.rref() #computes the reduced echelon form of A
 				</input>
 			</sage>
			
			Displaying multiple matrices can look messy with the default output. The <c>show</c> command formats the output in a more pleasing fashion:
 			<sage>
 				<input>
 					A=matrix(QQ, [[5,3,1], [1,4,-2]]);
					show(A) #displays the matrix named A, formatted
					show(A.rref())
 				</input>
 			</sage>
			
			
			
 			<p>
 				Note that while applying row operations in Sage changes the matrix being acted on, so that <m>A</m> would eventually be a matrix in reduced echelon form, the <c>rref</c> method creates a <em>new</em> matrix, which is in reduced echelon form and row equivalent to the original matrix, as illustrated below, where we see that the original matrix <m>B</m> is unchanged when its reduced echelon form is computed using <c>rref</c>.
 			</p>	
			
 			<sage>
 				<input>
					B=matrix(3,4, [[5,3,1,4], [1,4,-2,3], [0,3,2,6]]);
					C=B.rref();
					show(B);
					show(C)
 				</input>
			</sage>
			
 		</subsection>
		 
		
		<exercises>
			<p>
				Complete the following exercises in the GP 1-2 file in CoCalc by 8:00 AM on 8/25/2020.
			</p>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					Determine if each matrix is in reduced echelon form, echelon form, or neither. In the cases of echelon form or neither, state which property or properties are violated (see the definition on page 13 of the textbook).
					
					<ol>
						<li>
							<m>
								\begin{bmatrix}
								2 \amp -3 \amp 5 \\
								0 \amp 6 \amp 10
								\end{bmatrix}
							</m>
						</li>
						
						<li>
							<m>
								\begin{bmatrix}
								0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
								0 \amp 1 \amp 5
								\end{bmatrix}
							</m>
						</li>
						
						<li>
							<m>
								\begin{bmatrix}
								1 \amp 0 \amp -2 \amp 0 \amp 2 \\
								0 \amp 1 \amp 5 \amp 0 \amp 1 \\
								0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp 3 \\
								0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0
								\end{bmatrix}
							</m>
							
						</li>
						
						<li>
							<m>
								\begin{bmatrix}
								1 \amp -3 \amp 4 \amp -4 \\
								0 \amp 1 \amp 7 \amp -8 \\
								0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp 4
								\end{bmatrix}
							</m>
							
						</li>
						
						<li>
							<m>
								\begin{bmatrix}
								1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
								0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \amp 1 \\
								0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp 0
								\end{bmatrix}
							</m>
							
						</li>
						
					</ol>
					
				</statement>
				
			</exercise>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					The parts below are about the matrix <m>A=\begin{bmatrix}
					2 \amp -3 \amp 4 \amp -4 \amp 2 \\
				    0 \amp 0 \amp 7 \amp -8 \amp 1 \\
					0 \amp 0 \amp -1 \amp 4 \amp 3 
					\end{bmatrix}
					</m>.
					
					<ol>
						<li>
							Which columns of <m>A</m> are pivot columns? What are the entries of <m>A</m> in the pivot position in each pivot column?
						</li>
						
						<li>
							Assume <m>A</m> is the augmented matrix of a linear system with variables <m>x_1, x_2, x_3, x_4</m>. Which of these variables are basic variables? Which are free variables?
						</li>
					</ol>
					
					
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					What comments or questions do you have about the content of this assignment? 
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
		</exercises>	
	
		
		 
	 </section>
	 
	 
	 
	 
	 
	 <section xml:id="section-1-3">
		 <title>Guided Practice 1.3: Vector Equations</title>
		 
		 <introduction>
			 <title>Overview</title>
			 <p>
				 In Section 1.1, we introduced a new mathematical object, matrices, to help study linear systems of equations. In this section, we introduce <em>vectors</em>, another possibly more familiar mathematical object that will aid us. 
		 </p>
			
		 <p>
			 After describing vectors and their basic properties both algebraically and geometrically, the section begins relating them back to linear systems by introducing the very important concepts of <em>linear combinations</em> and <em>spans</em>. These two highly related concepts will be used repeatedly throughout the rest of the semester. Example 5 and the following discussion illustrate the strong connection between questions about linear combinations and questions about linear systems. The geometric descriptions should be used to help build intuition about these new concepts.
		 </p>
			

		 
		 </introduction>
		 
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-3-BLO">
			 <title>Basic Learning Objectives </title>
		<p>
			 You should be able to perform these tasks with reasonable fluency <em>when you arrive to class</em>.
			 
			 <ul>
				 <li>
				 	Compute sums and scalar multiples of column vectors in <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m>.
				 </li>
				 <li>
				 	List examples of linear combinations of a given set of vectors, specifying weights.
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 Translate among vector equations, linear systems, and augmented matrices.
				 </li>
				 <li>
				 	Define the span of a set of vectors and produce elements of the span of a given set of vectors.
				 </li>
			 </ul>
			
		 </p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-3-ALO">
			 <title>Advanced Learning Objectives </title>
		<p>
			In addition to mastering the basic objectives, here are the tasks you should be able to perform <em>after class, with practice</em>:
			 
			 <ul>
				 <li>
				 	Geometrically describe spans of sets of vectors in <m>\mathbb{R}^2</m> or <m>\mathbb{R}^3</m>.
				 </li>
				 <li>
				 	Determine if a given vector is in the span of a set of vectors.
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 Write a given vector as a linear combination of a set of other vectors, if possible.
				 </li>
			 </ul>
			
		 </p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-3-Resources">
			 <title>Resources</title>
			 <p>
				 <em>Reading</em>: Read Section 1.3 of the textbook, keeping the learning objectives in mind. It's helpful to write down new vocabulary words and notation along with short definitions/examples and to actively work along with the examples on your own paper. 
				 </p>
				  
				 <p>
				 	Even if you are somewhat familiar with vectors already, the beginning of the section should be a good refresher. Example 5 is the main example relating linear combinations to linear systems of equations. 
				 </p>
				 
			
			 
			 <p>
				 <em>Video</em>: The video below, from the 3Blue1Brown YouTube channel, focuses on the geometric and column vector perspectives of vectors and illustrates properties of vector arithmetic with some nice visuals. We will be using all three perspectives mentioned in the video during the semester.

				 	 <video youtube="fNk_zzaMoSs"/>
				</p> 
				
				
				<p> <em>Desmos</em>: Below is an interactive visual demonstration of linear combinations using Desmos. The starting vectors are <m>\mathbf{u}=(1,3)</m> and <m>\mathbf{v}=(-2,1)</m>. The vectors <m>c\mathbf{u}</m> and <m>d\mathbf{v}</m> are shown in blue, while the linear combination <m>c\mathbf{u} + d\mathbf{v}</m> is shown in purple. You can use the sliders for <m>c</m> and <m>d</m> to adjust their values and see how the linear combination changes. You can hit the play symbol on each slider or manually drag the slider to change the value. (To view the Desmos file below in its own (larger) window, <url href="https://www.desmos.com/calculator/9yocjg9etg"> click here</url>)
				
					 <interactive desmos="9yocjg9etg" aspect="16:9"/>
					 	
				 
			 </p>
			
			
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-3-Sage">
			 <title>Sage Commands</title>

 			<p>
 				When written as column vectors, vectors behave like <m>n \times 1</m> matrices, and they can be coded as such in Sage. As a shortcut, you can specify the number of rows (number of entries in the vector) and then include a single list of the entries.
			</p>
 			<sage>
 				<input>
 					u=matrix(3, [2,4,6]);
					v=matrix(5, [1,3,5,7,9]);
					show(u);
					show(v)
 				</input>
 			</sage>
			
			
				
			<p>
				However, we often want to treat vectors as vectors specifically. In Sage, we use the <c>vector</c> command, which is similar to the <c>matrix</c> command. We do not need to state the number of entries with this command; we simply list them out. Note also that Sage displays the result in row form (an alternative display form discussed in the textbook), but they are treated the same as column vectors.
				</p>
	 			<sage>
	 				<input>
	 					u=vector([2,4,6]);
						v=vector([1,3,5,7,9]);
						show(u);
						show(v);
						v
	 				</input>
	 			</sage>
				
				
			<p>
				The cell below demonstrates how to create linear combinations of vectors. Note that writing "5v1" will cause an error; a multiplication symbol is needed between the scalar and the vector.
			</p>
 			
 			<sage>
 				<input>
 					v1=vector([1,-3,4]);
					v2=vector([2,5,1]);
					print(v1+v2);
					print(v1-v2);
					print(5*v1);
					print(3*v1+7*v2);
					print(-3*v1-4*v2)
 				</input>
 			</sage>
			
			One nice consequence of Sage vectors is that we can easily create matrices out of them. We will usually want to create matrices whose columns are some given vectors. This is done using the <c>column_matrix</c> command and demonstrated below.
 			<sage>
 				<input>
 					u1=vector([1,2,3]);
					u2=vector([4,5,6]);
					u3=vector([7,8,9]);
					A=column_matrix([u1,u2,u3]);
					show(A)
 				</input>
 			</sage>
			
			
		
 		</subsection>
		 
		
		<exercises>
			<p>
				Complete the following exercises in the GP 1-3 file in CoCalc by 8:00 AM on 8/27/2020.
			</p>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					<p>
						Let <m>\mathbf{v}_1, \mathbf{v}_2, \mathbf{v}_3</m> be the vectors defined below. In a code cell, create and display three distinct linear combinations of the these three vectors, with at most one weight allowed to be 0 in each.
					</p>
					
					<p>
						<m>\mathbf{v}_1=\begin{bmatrix} 1 \\ 4 \\ 7 \end{bmatrix}, \mathbf{v}_2=\begin{bmatrix} 2 \\ 5 \\ 8 \end{bmatrix}, \mathbf{v}_3= \begin{bmatrix} 3 \\ 6 \\ 9 \end{bmatrix}</m>
					</p>
					
				</statement>
				
			</exercise>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					<p>
						Write an augmented matrix for the linear system that is equivalent to the vector equation below (define the matrix using Sage code or write it in a markdown cell).
					</p>
					
					<p>
						<m>x_1 \begin{bmatrix} 6 \\ -1 \\ 5 \end{bmatrix} + x_2 \begin{bmatrix} -3 \\4 \\ 0 \end{bmatrix} = \begin{bmatrix} 1 \\ -7 \\ -5 \end{bmatrix}</m>
					</p>
					
					
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					<p>
						Write a vector equation that is equivalent to the system of equations below.
					</p>
					
					<p>
						<md>
							<mrow> x_2 + 5x_3 \amp = 0</mrow>
							<mrow> 4x_1 + 6x_2 - x_3 \amp = 0</mrow>
							<mrow> -x_1 + 3x_2 - 8x_3 \amp = 0</mrow>
						</md>
					</p>
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					What comments or questions do you have about the content of this assignment? 
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
		</exercises>	
	
		
		 
	 </section>	 
	 
	 
	 
	 
	 
	 
	 <section xml:id="section-1-4">
		 <title>Guided Practice 1.4: The Matrix Equation <m>A\mathbf{x}=\mathbf{b}</m></title>
		 
		 <introduction>
			 <title>Overview</title>
			 <p>
				 In Section 1.3, we saw that we could reframe a system of linear equations as a single vector equation, in which one side was a linear combination of vectors. In this section, we continue to reframe systems of equations, this time by replacing a linear combination of vectors by a product of a matrix and a vector (see the definition on page 35). This creates a <em>matrix equation</em> which is equivalent to the vector equation and system of linear equations.
		 </p>
			
		 <p>
			 A major benefit of using matrix equations is that it helps us more easily analyze properties of linear systems. The discussion of this in the textbook culminates in Theorem 4, which relates consistency, linear combinations, spans, and pivot positions of a relevant matrix. This theorem is one of our main tools in answering problems and translating between different interpretations and perspectives. 
		 </p>
			
		<p>
			The remainder of the section focuses on properties of matrix-vector multiplication. Even though we will be doing most of our multiplication with technology, it is important to be able to do small matrix-vector computations by hand, so certainly read pages 38-39 and practice the "row-vector" rule. The top of page 39 also introduces the <em>identity matrix</em>, an important kind of matrix we will be seeing again.
		</p>	

		 
		 </introduction>
		 
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-4-BLO">
			 <title>Basic Learning Objectives </title>
		<p>
			 You should be able to perform these tasks with reasonable fluency <em>when you arrive to class</em>.
			 
			 <ul>
				 <li>
				 	State what it means for a set of vectors to span <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m>
				 </li>
				 <li>
				 	Compute the product of a matrix <m>A</m> and a vector as a linear combination of the columns of <m>A</m>.
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 Translate between vector equations and matrix equations.
				 </li>
				 <li>
				 	Compute the product of a matrix and a vector using the row-column rule.
				 </li>
			 </ul>
			
		 </p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-4-ALO">
			 <title>Advanced Learning Objectives </title>
		<p>
			In addition to mastering the basic objectives, here are the tasks you should be able to perform <em>after class, with practice</em>:
			 
			 <ul>
				 <li>
				 	Determine if a given matrix equation <m>A\mathbf{x}=\mathbf{b}</m> has a solution for every <m>\mathbf{b}</m>.
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 Determine if a set of vectors spans <m>\mathbf{R}^m</m>.
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 Explain why the statements in Theorem 4 are equivalent.
				 </li>
			 </ul>
			
		 </p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-4-Resources">
			 <title>Resources</title>
			 <p>
				 <em>Reading</em>: Read Section 1.4 of the textbook, keeping the learning objectives in mind. It's helpful to write down new vocabulary words and notation along with short definitions/examples and to actively work along with the examples on your own paper. 
				 </p>
				  
				 <p>
				 	Example 3, the discussion that follows, and Theorem 4 (all on page 37) form the conceptual core of this section. Example 5 explains the row-column rule for matrix-vector multiplication.
				 </p>
				 
			
			 
			 <p>
				 <em>Video</em>: In the video below, I demonstrate matrix-vector multiplication using both the definition and the row-column method. 

				 	 <video youtube="IFHq2rGHijQ"/>
				</p> 
				
				
			
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-4-Sage">
			 <title>Sage Commands</title>

 			<p>
 				Sage naturally understands multiplication of a vector by a matrix using the usual multiplication symbol (shift+8 on most keyboards). (Remember that Sage displays vectors in row form with parentheses, but correctly treats them as column vectors)
			</p>
 			<sage>
 				<input>
 					A=matrix([[1,2,3], [4,5,6], [7,8,9]]);
					B=matrix([[1,3,5], [7,8,9]]);
					v=vector([-1,3,-5]);
					show("A=",A," B=",B," v=",v)
					show("Av=",A*v)
					show("Bv=",B*v)
 				</input>
 			</sage>
			
			<p>
				Note that the dimensions have to match up (the number of columns of the matrix should match the number of entries in the vector); if they do not, then Sage will output an error (which you can see by executing the code below).
			</p>
			
 			<sage>
 				<input>
 					C=matrix([[1,2],[3,4], [5,6]])
					show("C=",C)
					v=vector([-1,3,-5]);
					show("v=",v)
					C*v
 				</input>
 			</sage>
			
				
			
			As a reminder, if vectors are already defined, you can create a matrix using them. To make a matrix with the vectors as columns, use the <c>column_matrix</c> command, shown below. To make a matrix with the vectors as rows, just use the <c>matrix</c> command with the vectors given inside brackets.
 			<sage>
 				<input>
 					u1=vector([1,2,3]);
					u2=vector([4,5,6]);
					u3=vector([7,8,9]);
					A=column_matrix([u1,u2,u3]);
					show("vectors as columns:",A)
					B=matrix([u1,u2,u3]);
					show("vectors as rows:",B)
 				</input>
 			</sage>
			
			
		
 		</subsection>
		 
		
		<exercises>
			<p>
				Complete the following exercises in the GP 1-4 file in CoCalc by 8:00 AM on Tuesday, 9/1/2020.
			</p>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					<p>
						Finish the sentence: "Saying the vectors <m>\mathbf{u}, \mathbf{v}</m> span <m>\mathbb{R}^2</m> means that ..."
					</p>
					
					
				</statement>
				
			</exercise>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					<p>
						Compute the product below by hand on paper using both the definition of matrix-vector multiplication and the row column rule (you do not need to show me your computations). Then confirm your answer by using Sage to compute the product.
					</p>
					
					<p>
						<m>\begin{bmatrix} 6 \amp 5 \\ -4 \amp -3 \\ 7 \amp 6 \end{bmatrix} \begin{bmatrix} 2 \\ -3 \end{bmatrix}</m>
					</p>
					
					
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					<p>
						Write down a matrix <m>A</m> and vector <m>\mathbf{b}</m> so that <m>A\mathbf{x}=\mathbf{b}</m> is the matrix equation that is equivalent to the vector equation below. (Write the matrix and vector using Sage code, with the names A and b)
					</p>
					
					<p>
						<m>x_1 \begin{bmatrix} 4 \\ -1 \\5 \\ -4 \end{bmatrix} + x_2 \begin{bmatrix} -5 \\ 3 \\ -5 \\ 1 \end{bmatrix} + x_3 \begin{bmatrix} 7 \\ -3 \\ 0 \\ 2 \end{bmatrix} = \begin{bmatrix} 6 \\ -8 \\ 0 \\ -7 \end{bmatrix}</m>
					</p>
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					What comments or questions do you have about the content of this assignment? 
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
		</exercises>	
	
		
		 
	 </section>	 
	 
	 
	 
	 	 
		 
	 
	 <section xml:id="section-1-5">
		 <title>Guided Practice 1.5: Solution Sets of Linear Systems</title>
		 
		 <introduction>
			 <title>Overview</title>
			 <p>
				 In the previous sections, we have studied systems of linear equations in many forms, using augmented matrices, vector equations, and matrix equations. In this section we delve deeper into how we describe the solution sets of linear systems, specifically in the case of infinitely many solutions (it is pretty easy to describe no solutions or 1 solution). This is accomplished using vector notation, which also opens up geometric descriptions of solution sets.
		 </p>
			
		 <p>
			 The section begins by examining <em>homogeneous</em> linear systems, lineasr systems whose matrix equations are of the form $A\mathbf{x}=\mathbf{0}$. These are easier to study and, surpisingly, an understanding of the solution sets of homogeneous systems is all we need to understand solution sets of <em>all</em> linear systems, as is made clear in Theorem 6.
		 </p>

		 
		 </introduction>
		 
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-5-BLO">
			 <title>Basic Learning Objectives </title>
		<p>
			 You should be able to perform these tasks with reasonable fluency <em>when you arrive to class</em>.
			 
			 <ul>
				 <li>
				 	Recognize when a linear system is homogeneous.
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 Determine when a homogeneous system has a nontrivial solution.
				 </li>
			 </ul>
			
		 </p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-5-ALO">
			 <title>Advanced Learning Objectives </title>
		<p>
			In addition to mastering the basic objectives, here are the tasks you should be able to perform <em>after class, with practice</em>:
			 
			 <ul>
				 <li>
				 	Describe the solution set of a homogeneous system as the span of a set of vectors.
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 Describe solutions to linear systems in parametric vector form.
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 Use Theorem 6 to geometrically compare and contrast the solution sets of <m>A\mathbf{x}=\mathbf{b}</m> and <m>A\mathbf{x}=\mathbf{0}</m>.
				 </li>
			 </ul>
			
		 </p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-5-Resources">
			 <title>Resources</title>
			 <p>
				 <em>Reading</em>: Read Section 1.5 of the textbook, keeping the learning objectives in mind. It's helpful to write down new vocabulary words and notation along with short definitions/examples and to actively work along with the examples on your own paper. 
				 </p>
				  
				 <p>
					 The discussion on pages 46 and 47 explains the geometric interpretation of solution sets of related homogeneous and non-homogeneous linear systems.
				 </p>
				 
			
				
			
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-5-Sage">
			 <title>Sage Commands</title>

 			<p>
 				No new Sage commands this time. We will continue to use Sage (in CoCalc) to help us row reduce matrices, but right now the focus is on interpreting and explaining. While Sage can row reduce a matrix, <em>we</em> then have to interpret it to describe the solution set.
			</p>
 			
		</subsection>
			
		<exercises>
			<p>
				Complete the following exercises in the GP 1-5 file in CoCalc by 8:00 AM on Thursday, 9/3/2020.
			</p>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					<p>
						For each linear system below, say if it is homogeneous or not homogeneous.
					</p>
					
					<p>
					<ol>
						<li>
							<md>
								<mrow> x_2 + 4x_3 \amp = -5</mrow>
								<mrow> x_1 + 3x_2 + 5x_3 \amp = -2</mrow>
								<mrow> 3x_1 + 7x_2 + 7x_3 \amp = 0</mrow>
							</md>
						</li>
						
						<li>
							<md>
								<mrow> x_2 + 4x_3 \amp = 0</mrow>
								<mrow> x_1 + 3x_2 + 5x_3 \amp = 0</mrow>
								<mrow> 3x_1 + 7x_2 + 7x_3 \amp = 0</mrow>
							</md>
						</li>
						
						<li>
							<md>
								<mrow> 5x_1 + 4x_4 \amp = 0</mrow>
								<mrow> 3x_2 - 8x_3 + 5x_4 \amp = 0</mrow>
								<mrow> 9x_1 + 2x_2 - 7x_3 \amp = 1</mrow>
							</md>
						</li>
						
						<li>
							<md>
								<mrow> 5x_1 + 4x_4 \amp = 0</mrow>
								<mrow> 3x_2 - 8x_3 + 5x_4 \amp = 0</mrow>
								<mrow> 9x_1 + 2x_2 - 7x_3 \amp = 0</mrow>
							</md>
						</li>
					</ol>
				</p>
					
				</statement>
				
			</exercise>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					<p>
						Each matrix below is the <em>coefficient matrix</em> (not augmented matrix) of a homogeneous system in echelon form. Without doing any computations, determine if the system has nontrivial solutions.
					</p>
					
					
					
					<p>
						<ol>
							<li>
								<m>\begin{bmatrix} 2 \amp 3 \amp 5 \\ 0 \amp 1 \amp 4 \end{bmatrix}</m>
							</li>
							
							<li>
								<m>\begin{bmatrix} 3 \amp 1 \\ 0 \amp 4 \\ 0 \amp 0 \end{bmatrix}</m>
							</li>

						</ol>
						
					</p>
					
					
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
			
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					What comments or questions do you have about the content of this assignment? 
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
		</exercises>	
	
		
		 
	 </section>	 
	 		 
		 
	 <section>
	 	
	 </section>
		 
		 
		 
	 
	 <section xml:id="section-1-7">
		 <title>Guided Practice 1.7: Linear Independence</title>
		 
		 <introduction>
			 <title>Overview</title>
			 <p>
				 So far we have discussed systems of linear equations, including writing them as vector equations and matrix equations, linear combinations and spans, and homogeneous systems. Conceptually, <em>linear independence,</em> the focus of this section, relates to all these topics. 
		 </p>
			
		 <p>
			 One way to think about linear independence is to compare and contrast with the idea of spans. With spans, we are focused on which vectors we can create from the building blocks we start with (i.e. what vectors can we write as linear combinations of the starting vectors). Think of the starting vectors as types of LEGO pieces, and the Span of those vectors as containing all LEGO creations you could build with those types of pieces. The notion of linear independence addresses the question "did we need <em>all</em> those starting types of LEGO pieces, or could we have started with fewer and still build everything?" 
		 </p>
		 
		 <p>
		 	In other words, linear independence is concerned with whether or not there is extra, redundant, information present. If a set of vectors is linearly <em>independent</em>, there is no redundant information; everyone one of those vectors is needed to build the Span. If the vectors are linearly <em>dependent</em>, then there is redundant information; we could build the same Span while getting rid of some of the starting vectors. 
		 </p>
		 
		 <p>
			 While that is a big picture introduction, the text explores linear independence from the perspective of matrix and vector equations (including the actual definition of linear independence and dependence) and relates it to geometry. It will be helpful to read this section multiple times while keeping the conceptual description above in mind; linear independence can be a tricky idea to master, but it will play a central role in many topics going forward.
		 </p>
		 
		 </introduction>
		 
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-7-BLO">
			 <title>Basic Learning Objectives </title>
		<p>
			 You should be able to perform these tasks with reasonable fluency <em>when you arrive to class</em>.
			 
			 <ul>
				 <li>
					 State what it means for a given set of vectors to be linearly independent.
					 
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 State what it means for a given set of vectors to be linearly dependent (without referencing linear independence).
				 </li>
				 
				 <li>
					 Quickly determine if a set of 2 vectors is linearly independent with minimal computation.
				 	
				 </li>
			 </ul>
			
		 </p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-7-ALO">
			 <title>Advanced Learning Objectives </title>
		<p>
			In addition to mastering the basic objectives, here are the tasks you should be able to perform <em>after class, with practice</em>:
			 
			 <ul>
				 <li>
					 Determine if a given set of vectors is linearly independent.
				 	
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 Find linear dependence relations among linearly dependent vectors.
					 
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 Apply Theorems 8 and 9 to appropriate sets of vectors to determine linear dependence.
				 </li>
			 </ul>
			
		 </p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-7-Resources">
			 <title>Resources</title>
			 <p>
				 <em>Reading</em>: Read Section 1.7 of the textbook, keeping the learning objectives in mind. It's helpful to write down new vocabulary words and notation along with short definitions/examples and to actively work along with the examples on your own paper. 
				 </p>
				  
				 <p>
					 For this section, do not worry too much about Theorem 7. Examples 2 and 3 are the most important ones to try to understand before coming to class.
				 </p>
				 
				 <p>
					 <em>Video</em>: This 10 minute video from the 3Blue1Brown YouTube channel (who we also used in Section 1.3) discusses linear combination, spans, and linear independence; the material on linear combinations and spans will be good review. It also discusses basis vectors, which we will formally examine later in the course, so while I do not recommend ignoring those parts, know that you do not need to understand or use them yet.
					 
					 <video youtube="k7RM-ot2NWY"></video>
				 </p>
				
			
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-7-Sage">
			 <title>Sage Commands</title>

 			<p>
 				Continuing a trend, there are no new commands to learn. Our primary computations are still row reducing an appropriate matrix to answer our questions. Computationally deciding if a set of given vectors is linearly independent involves creating a matrix with the vectors as columns and then row reducing it, which we already know how to do using the <c>column_matrix</c> command and <c>.rref()</c> method. The interpretation is then up to us. 
			</p>
 			
		</subsection>
			
		<exercises>
			<p>
				Complete the following exercises in the GP 1-7 file in CoCalc by 8:00 AM on Tuesday, 9/8/2020.
			</p>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					<p>
						Explain what it means for the set of vectors <m>\{\mathbf{u}, \mathbf{v}, \mathbf{w}\}</m> to be linearly dependent.
					</p>
					
				
					
				</statement>
				
			</exercise>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					<p>
						Explain how to quickly determine if a set of two vectors is linearly independent. 
					</p>
					
					
				
					
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
			
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					What comments or questions do you have about the content of this assignment? 
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
		</exercises>	
	
		
		 
	 </section>	 
	 		 
			 
			 
			 
			 
			 
			 
			 
			 
	 <section xml:id="section-1-8">
		 <title>Guided Practice 1.8: Introduction to Linear Transformations</title>
		 
		 <introduction>
			 <title>Overview</title>
			 <p>
				 The matrix equation <m>A\mathbf{x}=\mathbf{b}</m> was introduced in Section 1.4 as another way to notationally represent a vector equation, or system of linear equations, with <m>A</m> representing the coefficient matrix of the system. But the quantity <m>A\mathbf{x}</m> arises naturally in other contexts, such as computer graphics or dynamical systems. In these contexts we think of the matrix <m>A</m> as an object that "acts" on a vector <m>x</m> to produce a <em>new</em> vector <m>A\mathbf{x}</m>.
		 </p>
			
		 <p>
			 Mathematically, we describe such actions as <em>functions</em>, and we call the functions that arise from changing one vector into another vector <em>transformations</em>. Fortunately, while this is a completely differenent perspective on <m>A\mathbf{x}</m>, and as a result the kinds of questions we ask are now different, we can still use the tools of row reduction and pivots to answer these questions by rephrasing them in terms of systems of equations or matrix equations. Example 1 of this section is a great illustration of how these ideas all combine together.
		 </p>
		 
		 <p>
		 	While there are many possible kinds of transformations, in this class we will study <em>linear transformations</em> (as the name of the course itself might imply), which are formally defined roughly halfway through the section. Linear transformations arise naturally in many applications, and all transformations defined by multiplication by a matrix are linear transformations (we will explore the other direction of this in the next section). The properties of linear transformations make them particularly nice to analyze, and we will take full advantage of that fact. 
		 </p>
		
		 
		 </introduction>
		 
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-8-BLO">
			 <title>Basic Learning Objectives </title>
		<p>
			 You should be able to perform these tasks with reasonable fluency <em>when you arrive to class</em>.
			 
			 <ul>
				 <li>
					 Describe what transformations and matrix transformations are.
					 
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 Identify the domain and codomain of a given matrix transformation.
				 </li>
				 
				 <li>
				 	Given a transformation <m>T</m>, compute the image of a specific vector under the action of <m>T</m>.
				 </li>
				 
				 <li>
					 Define what it means for a transformation to be a linear transformation.
				 	
				 </li>
			 </ul>
			
		 </p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-8-ALO">
			 <title>Advanced Learning Objectives </title>
		<p>
			In addition to mastering the basic objectives, here are the tasks you should be able to perform <em>after class, with practice</em>:
			 
			 <ul>
				 <li>
					 Given a transformation <m>T</m>, determine if a given vector is in the range of <m>T</m>.
				 	
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 Determine if a given transformation is a linear transformation.
					 
					 
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 Geometrically describe the actions of projection, shear, and scaling matrix transformations.
				 </li>
			 </ul>
			
		 </p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-8-Resources">
			 <title>Resources</title>
			 
			 <p>
				 <em>Video</em>: Begin by watching this 3:31 video clip of a 3Blue1Brown video (the rest of the video will be watched for Section 1.9). This video provides great visualizations and intuition for what a linear transformation is.
				 
				 <video youtube="kYB8IZa5AuE" end="211"></video>
			 </p>
			 
			<p> <em>Desmos</em>: Below is an interactive visual demonstration of linear transformations using Desmos that lets you create similar images as those in the video. The base <m>xy</m>-grid is shown in dashed black and blue lines, and this grid transformed by the matrix <m>\begin{bmatrix} a \amp b \\ c \amp d \end{bmatrix}</m> is shown in purple and green. You can hit the play symbol on each slider or manually drag the slider to change the value of each entry of the matrix and create your own tranformation visuals. To <em>animate</em> the transformation, click play next to the "s" slider. 
		</p>
			
		<p> This activity is best experienced in a separate window where everything is larger and easier to see. To view the Desmos activity below in its own (much larger) window, <url href="https://www.desmos.com/calculator/vi5obzi2hd"> click here</url>)
			
				 <interactive desmos="mxb2phnn4w" aspect="16:9"/>
				 	
		 </p>
			 
			 <p>
				 <em>Reading</em>: After watching the video and playing around with the Desmos activity, read Section 1.8 of the textbook, keeping the learning objectives in mind. I recommend taking notes by writing down new vocabulary words and notation along with short definitions/examples, as well as actively working along with the examples on your own paper. 
				 </p>
				  

				
				
			
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-8-Sage">
			 <title>Sage Commands</title>

 			<p>
 				Applying a matrix transformation to a vector involves multiplying a vector by a matrix. The cell below reviews these commands. Answering questions about these matrix transformations will often require row reduction, which we continue to do using the <c>.rref()</c> method.
				
				
	 			<sage>
	 				<input>
	 					v=vector([1,2,3,4]);
						A=column_matrix([[1,3], [2,4], [5,1], [-1,-6]]);
						show("A=",A);
						show("v=",v);
						show("The image of v under the action by A is Av=",A*v)
	 				</input>
	 			</sage>
				
				
			</p>
 			
			<p>
				Note that in the example above, <m>A</m> is a <m>2\times 4</m> matrix that maps an input vector from <m>\mathbb{R}^4</m> (matching the number of columns of <m>A</m>) to an output vector in <m>\mathbb{R}^2</m> (matching the number of rows of <m>A</m>).
			</p>
			
			
			
			
			
			
		</subsection>
			
		<exercises>
			<p>
				Complete the following exercises in the GP 1-8 file in CoCalc by 8:00 AM on Tuesday, 9/15/2020.
			</p>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					<p>
						Consider the transformation <m>T</m> defined by <m>T(\mathbf{x})=A \mathbf{x}</m>, where <m>A=\begin{bmatrix} 4 \amp 1 \amp 0 \\
						-1 \amp 5 \amp 2 \\
						3 \amp 2 \amp 1 \\
						1 \amp 5 \amp 0
						\end{bmatrix}</m>. What are the domain and codomain of <m>T</m>? (Write your answer as a complete sentence using <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m> (written as <c>$\mathbb{R}^n$</c>) with the correct numbers in place of <m>n</m>).
					</p>
					
				
					
				</statement>
				
			</exercise>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					<p>
						Define a transformation <m>T:\mathbb{R}^3 \to \mathbb{R}^3</m> by <m>T(\mathbf{x})=\begin{bmatrix} 1 \amp 0 \amp -2 \\ 2 \amp 3 \amp 1 \\ -5 \amp 2 \amp 4\end{bmatrix} \mathbf{x}</m>. Compute <m>T(\mathbf{v})</m>, where <m>\mathbf{v}=\begin{bmatrix} 5 \\ 3 \\ -2 \end{bmatrix}.</m> 
					</p>
					
					
				
					
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					Explain in words (without using mathematical notation) what the <em>linear</em> in "linear transformation" means. That is, what does it mean for a transformation to be a <em>linear</em> transformation?
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					What comments or questions do you have about the content of this assignment? 
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
		</exercises>	
	
	
		
		 
	 </section>	 			 
			 
			 
			 





	 <section xml:id="section-1-9">
		 <title>Guided Practice 1.9: The Matrix of a Linear Transformation</title>
		 
		 <introduction>
			 <title>Overview</title>
			 <p>
				 Because we have already done so much work with matrices, it would be nice to put that knowledge to work when it comes to linear transformations. That is, we would like to be able to describe all linear transformations as matrix transformations. As Example 1 in the section demonstrates, this is actually something we can always do! (At least as long as the linear transformation is mapping from <m>\mathbb{R}^m</m> to <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m>)
		 </p>
			
		 <p>
			 After Example 1, the book discusses the general strategy for finding the <em>standard matrix</em> of a linear transformation; in other words, the matrix formula for the transformation. We then see the standard matrices for many geometric transformations of the plane, including rotations, reflections, scaling, shears, and projections. Some of these will be explored in more detail in an upcoming project on computer graphics.  
		 </p>
		 
		 <p>
		 	The section concludes by discussing the properties of a function being <em>one-to-one</em> or <em>onto</em>. Once we have a matrix formula, these properties directly correspond to statements about the columns of the matrix being linear independent or spanning <m>\mathbb{R}^m</m>; see Theorem 12. Linear transformations will continue to be an important topic, and this section gives us some of the main tools to help analyze them.
		 </p>
		
		 
		 </introduction>
		 
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-9-BLO">
			 <title>Basic Learning Objectives </title>
		<p>
			 You should be able to perform these tasks with reasonable fluency <em>when you arrive to class</em>.
			 
			 <ul>
				 <li>
					 Explain how to find the standard matrix of a linear transformation <m>T: \mathbb{R}^n \to \mathbb{R}^m</m>.
					 
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 Given a linear transformation <m>T: \mathbb{R}^n \to \mathbb{R}^m</m>, find its standard matrix.
				 </li>
				 
				 <li>
				 	Find the standard matrix of the linear transformation that rotates each point of <m>\mathbb{R}^2</m> counterclockwise by <m>\theta</m> radians.
				 </li>
				 
			 </ul>
			
		 </p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-9-ALO">
			 <title>Advanced Learning Objectives </title>
		<p>
			In addition to mastering the basic objectives, here are the tasks you should be able to perform <em>after class, with practice</em>:
			 
			 <ul>
				 <li>
					 Give geometric descriptions of the matrix transformations in Tables 1-4.
				 	
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 Explain what it means for a linear transformation to be one-to-one or onto, without referencing a matrix.
					 
					 
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 Use the standard matrix of a linear transformation <m>T</m> to determine if <m>T</m> is one-to-one or onto.
				 </li>
			 </ul>
			
		 </p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-9-Resources">
			 <title>Resources</title>
			 
			 <p>
				 <em>Video</em>: Begin by watching the rest of the 3Blue1Brown video that you watched for Section 1.8. his video provides great visualizations and intuition for describing the standard matrix of a linear transformation. In the video, they use "i hat" and "j hat" for what the textbook calls <m>\mathbf{e}_1=\begin{bmatrix} 1 \\ 0 \end{bmatrix}</m> and <m>\mathbf{e}_2=\begin{bmatrix} 0 \\ 1 \end{bmatrix}</m>.
				 
				 <video youtube="kYB8IZa5AuE" start="197"></video>
			 </p>
			 
			<p> <em>Desmos</em>: Below is another interactive visual demonstration of linear transformations using Desmos that lets you experiment with standard matrices and view the action of a matrix transformation on a square or an asymmetric shape. The file shows the images of <m>\mathbf{e}_1</m> and <m>\mathbf{e}_2</m> to further connect to the standard matrix idea. You can find the standard matrix of a particular transformation by dragging these images around and looking at the slider values of <m>a,b,c,</m> and <m>d</m>.
		</p>
			
		<p> This activity is best experienced in a separate window where everything is larger and easier to see. To view the Desmos activity below in its own (much larger) window, <url href="https://www.desmos.com/calculator/zzsuxd0acx"> click here</url>)
			
				 <interactive desmos="zzsuxd0acx" aspect="16:9"/>
				 	
		 </p>
			 
			 <p>
				 <em>Reading</em>: After watching the video and playing around with the Desmos activity, read Section 1.9 of the textbook, keeping the learning objectives in mind. I recommend taking notes by writing down new vocabulary words and notation along with short definitions/examples, as well as actively working along with the examples on your own paper. 
				 </p>
				  

				
				
			
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-1-9-Sage">
			 <title>Sage Commands</title>

 			<p>
 				There is no Sage command for "find the standard matrix"; we have to do that part ourselves. Once we have the standard matrix, we can row reduce it using .rref() and analyze it as we have been doing. However, we can use Sage to explore the geometric actions of linear transformations (this will be the main focus of Project 3). The code below creates the letter N, plots it, and then plots a linear transformation applied to the letter N. Try changing the entries of A in the third cell to see what effect it has.
			
				
	 			<sage>
	 				<input>
	 					d=matrix(QQ, 2, 9, [[0, 0.5, 0.5, 6, 6, 5.5, 5.5, 0, 0], [0, 0, 6.42, 0, 8, 8, 1.58, 8, 0]]); 
						show(d); #each column represents a point in the plane
						
	 				</input>
	 			</sage>
				
				
				<sage>
					<input>
						N_0=list_plot(d.columns(), plotjoined=true, aspect_ratio=1, color='purple'); 
						N_0 # the above command "connects the dots" to create a picture
					</input>
				</sage>
				
				<sage>
					<input>
						A=matrix(QQ, [[1,0.25,],[0,1]]); show(A) #the standard matrix of a linear transformation
						d_1=A*d; #apply the transformation to the original points
						N_1=list_plot(d_1.columns(), plotjoined=true, aspect_ratio=1, color='blue'); 
						# the above command "connects the dots" on the transformed image
						N_0+N_1 #display the original image and the transformed image
					</input>
				</sage>
				
			</p>
 			

			
			
			
			
			
			
		</subsection>
			
		<exercises>
			<p>
				Complete the following exercises in the GP 1-9 file in CoCalc by 8:00 AM on Thursday, 9/17/2020.
			</p>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					<p>
						Consider a linear transformation <m>T: \mathbb{R}^3 \to \mathbb{R}^2</m>. Explain how you would find the standard matrix of <m>T</m>. What would the dimensions of this matrix be? (rows by columns)
					</p>
					
				
					
				</statement>
				
			</exercise>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					<p>
						Suppose <m>T: \mathbb{R}^2\to \mathbb{R}^3</m> is a linear transformation such that <m>T\left( \begin{bmatrix} 1 \\ 0 \end{bmatrix} \right) = \begin{bmatrix} 2 \\ 8 \\ 1 \end{bmatrix}</m> and <m>T\left( \begin{bmatrix} 0 \\ 1 \end{bmatrix} \right) = \begin{bmatrix} 4 \\ 3 \\ 7 \end{bmatrix}</m>. Determine the standard matrix of <m>T</m>.
					</p>
					
					
				
					
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					What is the standard matrix of the rotation by <m>\pi</m> radians in the counterclockwise direction?
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					What comments or questions do you have about the content of this assignment? 
				</statement>
			</exercise>
			
		</exercises>	
	
	
		
		 
	 </section>	 			 
			 





			 
		 
	 
	 
 </chapter>
 
 
 
 
 
 
 <chapter xml:id="chapter-Matrices">
	 <title>Matrix Algebra</title>
			 
		 
		 
		 



 <section xml:id="section-2-1">
	 <title>Guided Practice 2.1: Matrix Operations</title>
	 
	 <introduction>
		 <title>Overview</title>
		 <p>
			 In the last two sections, we saw how matrices could be used to represent and describe linear transformations. In this section, we investigate matrices and their algebraic properties in more detail, while still relating back to linear transformations.
	 </p>
		
	 <p>
		 The majority of the section is devoted to setting notation and carefully describing and defining algebraic operations involving matrices, so that we may use these properties in the future to continue to solve problems about systems of equations and linear transformations.
	 </p>
	
	 
	 </introduction>
	 
	 
	 <subsection xml:id="subsection-2-1-BLO">
		 <title>Basic Learning Objectives </title>
	<p>
		 You should be able to perform these tasks with reasonable fluency <em>when you arrive to class</em>.
		 
		 <ul>
			 <li>
				 Use correct notation for matrix entries and identify and create diagonal matrices and zero matrices.
				 
			 </li>
			 <li>
				 Compute matrix sums and scalar multiples of matrices.
			 </li>
			 
			 <li>
			 	Determine if two matrices can be added together or multiplied together by examining their dimensions.
			 </li>
			 
			 <li>
			 	Perform matrix multiplication using both the definition and the row-column method.
			 </li>
		 </ul>
		
	 </p>
	 </subsection>
	 
	 <subsection xml:id="subsection-2-1-ALO">
		 <title>Advanced Learning Objectives </title>
	<p>
		In addition to mastering the basic objectives, here are the tasks you should be able to perform <em>after class, with practice</em>:
		 
		 <ul>
			 <li>
				 Interpret matrix multiplication as the composition of linear transformations.
			 	
			 </li>
			 <li>
				 Compute powers and the transpose of a matrix.
				 
				 
			 </li>
			 <li>
				 Use the properties in Theorems 1,2,3 while performing computations with matrices.
			 </li>
		 </ul>
		
	 </p>
	 </subsection>
	 
	 <subsection xml:id="subsection-2-1-Resources">
		 <title>Resources</title>
		 
		 <p>
			 <em>Video</em>: Begin by watching the 3Blue1Brown video below about matrix multiplication and its connection to composition of functions. This video has a great explanation and visualization of how we want to <em>conceptualize</em> matrix multiplication. This perspective is very useful when and will make thinking about matrix multiplication much easier.
			 
			 <video youtube="XkY2DOUCWMU" start="121"></video>
		 </p>
		 

		 
		 <p>
			 <em>Reading</em>: After watching the video, read Section 2.1 of the textbook, keeping the learning objectives in mind. There is a lot of notation introduced and a lot of algebraic properties given. The main thing to keep in mind is that matrix multiplication usually works algebraically just like usual "number multiplication", except that in general, <m>AB \neq BA</m>. I recommend taking notes by writing down new vocabulary words and notation along with short definitions/examples, as well as actively working along with the examples on your own paper. 
			 </p>
			  

			
			
		
	 </subsection>
	 
	 <subsection xml:id="subsection-2-1-Sage">
		 <title>Sage Commands</title>

		<p>
			This section introduces several new operations on matrices: addition, multiplication, scalar multiplication, powers, and transpose. The Sage cells below demonstrate how to implement these commands.
		</p>
		
		<p>
			Matrix addition:
			
			<sage>
				<input>
					A=matrix([[1,3,5], [2,4,6]]);
					B=matrix([[1,-1], [4,2]]);
					C=matrix([[5,6], [1,3]]);
					show("B=", B)
					show("C=", C)
					show("B+C=", B+C); #add matrices using +
				</input>
			</sage>
		</p>
			
			
		<p>
			Scalar multiplication:
			
			<sage>
				<input>
					show("A=", A)
					show("5A=", 5*A); #multiply by a number using *
				</input>
			</sage>
			
		</p>
			
		<p>
			Matrix multiplication:
			
			<sage>
				<input>
					show("B=", B, "C=", C)
					show("BC=", B*C)
					show("B=", B, "A=", A)
					show("BA=", B*A)
				</input>
			</sage>
		
			<sage>
				<input>
					#A*B will raise an error because the dimensions do not match
					A*B
				</input>
			</sage>
			
		</p>
			
			
		<p>
			Matrix powers:
			
			<sage>
				<input>
					#only square matrices can multiply themselves
					show("C=", C)
					show("C^5=", C^5) #use the symobl ^ for powers
				</input>
			</sage>
			
			
		</p>
		
		<p>
			Transpose:
			
			<sage>
				<input>
					show("A=", A)
					show("Transpose of A is", A.transpose()) #use the .transpose() method
					show("B=", B)
					show("Transpose of B is", B.transpose())
				</input>
			</sage>
			
		</p>
			
			
		<p>
			The cell below contains code that draws the letter N (named N_0) and defines three linear transformations; a shearing S, a rotation R, and a dilation D. The matrix A is then defined as a product of these transformations.
			
		</p>
		
		<p> I encourage you to change the definition of A to see the effect of doing the transformations repeatedly or in a different order. To see the definition of A, scroll down in the Sage cell below.
			
 			<sage>
 				<input>
 					d=matrix(QQ, 2, 9, [[0, 0.5, 0.5, 6, 6, 5.5, 5.5, 0, 0], [0, 0, 6.42, 0, 8, 8, 1.58, 8, 0]]); 
					N_0=list_plot(d.columns(), plotjoined=true, aspect_ratio=1, color='purple'); 
					
					# a horizontal shear matrix:
					S=matrix(RDF, [[1,0.25,],[0,1]]); 
					
					# a rotation matrix:
					R=matrix(RDF, [[cos(pi/4), -sin(pi/4)], [sin(pi/4), cos(pi/4)]]); 
					
					# a dilation matrix
					D=matrix(RDF, [[2, 0], [0,2]]); 
					
					# shear, followed by rotation, followed by dilation
					A=D*R*S; 
					d_1=A*d; #transformation applied
					
					N_1=list_plot(d_1.columns(), plotjoined=true, aspect_ratio=1, color='blue'); 
					N_0+N_1
					
 				</input>
 			</sage>
			
		</p>
		

		
		
		
		
		
		
	</subsection>
		
	<exercises>
		<p>
			Complete the following exercises in the GP 2-1 file in CoCalc by 8:00 AM on Tuesday, 9/22/2020.
		</p>
		
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>
					Let <m>A=\begin{bmatrix} -1 \amp 7 \\ 5 \amp 4 \\ 2 \amp -3 \end{bmatrix}</m>. 
					
					<ol>
						<li>
							What are the diagonal entries of <m>A</m>?
						</li>
						
						<li>
							What is value of the entry <m>a_{12}</m>?
						</li>
					</ol>
	
				</p>
				
			
				
			</statement>
			
		</exercise>
		
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>
					Let <m>A, B</m> be <m>3\times 4</m> matrices, and let <m>C</m> be a <m>4\times 4 </m> matrix.
					
					<ol>
						<li>
							Which of these matrices can be added together?
						</li>
						
						<li>
							<p>
								Which of the following matrix products can actually be done?
							</p>
							
							<p>
								<m>AB, AC, BA, CA, BC, CB, A^2, B^2, C^2</m>
							</p>
						</li>
					</ol>
					
				</p>
				
			
				
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				Pick one of the matrix products above that could actually be carried out. Then write down actual matrices with the correct dimensions (with at most 2 entries of 0) and carry out the multiplication by hand on paper using both methods discussed in this section. Then perform the multiplication in a Sage code cell.

				(So if you decide to do a matrix product that involves <m>A</m>, create and write down a <m>3\times 4</m> matrix with actual number entries of your choice (with at most 2 of them being 0) and call in <m>A</m>)
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				What comments or questions do you have about the content of this assignment? 
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		
	</exercises>	


	
	 
 </section>	 			 
		 
	
	
	
	
	
 <section xml:id="section-2-2">
	 <title>Guided Practice 2.2: The Inverse of a Matrix</title>
	 
	 <introduction>
		 <title>Overview</title>
		 <p>
			 Now that we understand how to add and multiply matrices, we can think a little deeper about these operations. In particular, since we are interested in solving matrix equations of the form <m>A\mathbf{x}=\mathbf{b}</m>, we want to explore matrix multiplication a little more.
	 </p>
		
	 <p>
		 Remembering that matrix equations are generalizations of simple linear equations, we look to a simple linear equation as a motivating example. Consider the equation <m>5x=3</m>. To solve it, we multiply both sides by <m>1/5</m>, the multiplicative inverse of <m>5</m>, because <m>\dfrac{1}{5}\cdot 5=1</m>. This yields <m>x=\dfrac{1}{5}\cdot 3.</m>
	 </p>
	
	 <p>
		 To accomplish something similar for the matrix equation <m>A\mathbf{x}=\mathbf{b}</m>, we need a matrix <m>C</m> such that <m>CA=I</m>, where <m>I</m> is an appropriately sized identity matrix. We call such a matrix an <m>inverse</m> matrix. This section explores the properties of inverse matrices, how to determine if they exist, and how to find them if they do. 
	 </p>
	
	 
	 </introduction>
	 
	 
	 <subsection xml:id="subsection-2-2-BLO">
		 <title>Basic Learning Objectives </title>
	<p>
		 You should be able to perform these tasks with reasonable fluency <em>when you arrive to class</em>.
		 
		 <ul>
			 <li>
				 State what it means for a square matrix to be invertible.
				 
			 </li>
			 <li>
				 Compute the determinant of a <m>2\times 2</m> matrix and use it to determine if the matrix is invertible.
			 </li>
			 
			 <li>
			 	Find the entries of the inverse of an invertible <m>2\times 2</m> matrix.
			 </li>
			 
		 </ul>
		
	 </p>
	 </subsection>
	 
	 <subsection xml:id="subsection-2-2-ALO">
		 <title>Advanced Learning Objectives </title>
	<p>
		In addition to mastering the basic objectives, here are the tasks you should be able to perform <em>after class, with practice</em>:
		 
		 <ul>
			 <li>
				 Correctly use the properties of inverse matrices in Theorems 5 and 6.
			 	
			 </li>
			 <li>
				 Use row reduction to determine if a square matrix is invertible.
				 
				 
			 </li>
			 <li>
				 Use row reduction to find the inverse of a an invertible matrix.
			 </li>
		 </ul>
		
	 </p>
	 </subsection>
	 
	 <subsection xml:id="subsection-2-2-Resources">
		 <title>Resources</title>
		 
		 <p>
			 <em>Reading</em>: Read Section 2.2 of the textbook, keeping the learning objectives in mind. You can ignore the part about Elementary matrices. Theorems 5 and 7 are the main results of the section. After doing the reading, watch the video below to gain some geometric insight into inverse matrices.
			 </p>
		 
		 
		 <p>
			 <em>Video</em>: Watch the selected segment of the 3Blue1Brown video below about the geometric interpretation of matrix inverses, using the linear transformation perspective of matrix multiplication. The determinant is mentioned in this video, and is defined for <m>2 \times 2</m> matrices in the reading. We will explore the determinant in much more detail in Chapter 3.
			 
			 <video youtube="uQhTuRlWMxw" start="130" end="403"></video>
		 </p>
		 

		 

			  

			
			
		
	 </subsection>
	 
	 <subsection xml:id="subsection-2-2-Sage">
		 <title>Sage Commands</title>

		<p>
			This section introduces matrix inverses. There are two main ways to directly compute the inverse of matrix using Sage: using an exponent of <m>-1</m> and using the <c>.inverse()</c> method. These are both illustrated below. If a matrix is singular or not square, Sage will throw an error.
		</p>
		
		<p>
			
			<sage>
				<input>
					A=matrix([[1,-1], [4,2]]);
					show(A^-1)
					show(A.inverse())
					show(A^-1*A)
					show(A*A.inverse())
				</input>
			</sage>
			
			<sage>
				<input>
					# nonsquare matrix
					B=matrix([[1,3,5], [2,4,6]]);
					B^-1
				</input>
			</sage>
			
			<sage>
				<input>
					# singular matrix
					C=matrix([[5,6], [10,12]]);
					C.inverse()
				</input>
			</sage>
		</p>
			
			
	</subsection>
		
	<exercises>
		<p>
			No exercises for this section.
		</p>
		
		
	</exercises>	


	
	 
 </section>	 			
	
	
	
	
	
	
	
	
	
	
 </chapter>

 
 <chapter xml:id="chapter-3">
 	 <title>The Determinant</title>
	
	 <section xml:id="section-3-1">
		 <title>Guided Practice 3.1, 3.2: The Determinant and its Properties</title>
	 
		 <introduction>
			 <title>Overview</title>
			 <p>
				 We saw that for a <m>2\times 2</m> matrix <m>A=\begin{bmatrix} a \amp b \\ c \amp d \end{bmatrix}</m>, the value of quantity <m>\det(A)=ad-bc</m> determines whether or not the matrix <m>A</m> is invertible. This quantity <m>\det(A)</m> is called the <em>determinant</em> of <m>A</m>, and the main goal of this chapter is to identify the determinant of larger square matrices and describe its properties.
		 </p>
		
		 <p>
			 The main ways of computing the determinant of matrices larger than <m>2\times 2</m> are cofactor expansion (see Example 1 on page 167) and by using row reduction and properties of the determinant (see Example 2 on page 172). Useful shortcuts include the results of Theorem 2 and Theorem 6 in Chapter 3. While we will often use technology to compute determinants of specific matrices, an understanding of how the determinant is computed will help us relate it to other topics as we proceed.
		 </p>
	
		 <p>
			 While the question "is the determinant 0 or not 0" usually has the most relevance, when the determinant is nonzero, its value has additional geometric meaning. This is explored in the video resource for this section, as well as in Section 3.3 of the textbook. The geometric perspective presents the best conceptual way of viewing the determinant.
		 </p>
	
	 
		 </introduction>
	 
	 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-3-1-BLO">
			 <title>Basic Learning Objectives </title>
		<p>
			 You should be able to perform these tasks with reasonable fluency <em>when you arrive to class</em>.
		 
			 <ul>
				 <li>
					 Given a square matrix <m>A</m>, write down a given submatrix <m>A_{ij}</m>.
				 
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 Use Theorem 2 of Section 3.1 to quickly compute the determinant of a triangular matrix.
				 </li>
			 
				 <li>
					 Describe how elementary row operations affect the determinant of a square matrix.
				 	
				 </li>
			 
			 </ul>
		
		 </p>
		 </subsection>
	 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-3-1-ALO">
			 <title>Advanced Learning Objectives </title>
		<p>
			In addition to mastering the basic objectives, here are the tasks you should be able to perform <em>after class, with practice</em>:
		 
			 <ul>
				 <li>
					 State and use the multiplicative property of the determinant.
			 	
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 Use cofactor expansion to manually compute the determinant of a <m>3 \times 3</m> matrix.
				 
				 
				 </li>
				 <li>
					 Use row reduction to compute determinants of square matrices.
				 </li>
			 </ul>
		
		 </p>
		 </subsection>
	 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-3-1-Resources">
			 <title>Resources</title>
			 
			 
			 <p>
				 <em>Video</em>: First watch the 3Blue1Brown video below about the geometric meaning and interpretation of the determinant, using the linear transformation perspective of matrix multiplication. 
			 
				 <video youtube="Ip3X9LOh2dk"></video>
			 </p>
		 
			 <p>
				 <em>Reading</em>: Read Sections 3.1 and 3.2 of the textbook. In Section 3.1, try to follow along with the examples, where they demonstrate using cofactor expansion. Theorem 2 is an important result that relates to the big result of Section 3.2. In section 3.2, Theorems 3, 4, and 6 are the big ones to focus on, with Examples 1 and 2 being the most important examples.
				 </p>
		 
		 

		 

		 

			  

			
			
		
		 </subsection>
	 
		 <subsection xml:id="subsection-3-1-Sage">
			 <title>Sage Commands</title>

			<p>
				To compute the determinant of a square matrix using Sage, use det(A) or A.det(), as shown below.
			</p>
		
			<p>
			
				<sage>
					<input>
						A=matrix([[1,-1], [4,2]]);
						show(A)
						show(det(A))
					</input>
				</sage>
			
				<sage>
					<input>
						B=matrix([[1,2,3], [4,5,6], [7,3,1]])
						show(B)
						show(B.det())
					</input>
				</sage>
			
				<sage>
					<input>
						# singular matrix
						C=matrix([[5,6], [10,12]]);
						show(C)
						show(C.det())
					</input>
				</sage>
			</p>
			
			
		</subsection>
		
		<exercises>
			<p>
				Complete the following exercises in the GP 3-1 file in CoCalc by 8:00 AM on Tuesday, 10/6/2020.
			</p>
		
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					<p>
						Let <m>A=\begin{bmatrix} 2 \amp -4 \amp 1\\ 0 \amp 3 \amp 5\\ 7 \amp -1 \amp 4 \end{bmatrix}</m>. Write down the submatrices <m>A_{1,2}</m> and <m>A_{3,1}</m>.
					
						
	
					</p>
				
			
				
				</statement>
			
			</exercise>
		
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					<p>
						Let <m>B=\begin{bmatrix} 3 \amp 9 \amp 101 \amp 24 \\ 0 \amp -2 \amp 99 \amp 11 \\ 0 \amp 0 \amp 5 \amp 78 \\ 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 2 \end{bmatrix}</m>. Without using technology, compute the determinant of <m>B</m>. Explain how you computed your answer.
					
						
					
					</p>
				
			
				
				</statement>
			</exercise>
		
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					<p>
					Suppose <m>A</m> is a <m>3 \times 3</m> matrix and <m>\det(A)=5.</m> If <m>B</m> is the matrix that <m>A</m> becomes after adding <m>-5</m> times the first row of <m>A</m> to the third row of <m>A</m>, what is <m>\det(B)</m>?
				</p>
				</statement>
			</exercise>
		
			<exercise>
				<statement>
					What comments or questions do you have about the material? 
				</statement>
			</exercise>
		
		</exercises>	


	
	 
	 </section>	 			
	
	
	
 </chapter>
 
 



<chapter xml:id="chapter-4">
	 <title>Vector Spaces</title>

 <section xml:id="section-4-1">
	 <title>Guided Practice 4.1: Vector Spaces and Subspaces</title>
 
	 <introduction>
		 <title>Overview</title>
		 <p>
			 Up to this point in the class, when we have said "vector," we have meant a list of numbers, or possibly an arrow in the plane or space. But if you closely examine the definitions of linear combinations, spans, linear independence, and linear transformations, the only properties of vectors that were needed were the ability to add vectors and multiply vectors by scalars (in the "normal" way with associative and distributive laws). 
	 </p>
	
	 <p>
		 This chapter takes that observation and runs with it. The first section starts by defining a vector not as a specific type of object, but as a kind of object that satisfies the usual properties of addition and scalar multiplication. We then see several examples of spaces with objects that satisfy these properties and call them "vector spaces." Throughout the chapter we will see that most of the work we have done so far with <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m> vectors can also be applied to other vector spaces.
	 </p>

	 <p>
		 The other main topic of the section is that of <em>subspaces</em> of a vector space. Algebraically, these are related to spans of sets of vectors, and you can think of them as the equivalent of lines or planes through the origin in <m>\mathbb{R}^2</m> or <m>\mathbb{R}^3</m>. In future sections we will investigate several special kinds of subspaces that arise from systems of equations and linear transformations.
	 </p>

 
	 </introduction>
 
 
	 <subsection xml:id="subsection-4-1-BLO">
		 <title>Basic Learning Objectives </title>
	<p>
		 You should be able to perform these tasks with reasonable fluency <em>when you arrive to class</em>.
	 
		 <ul>
			 <li>
				 Give examples of vector spaces other than <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m>.
			 
			 </li>
			 <li>
				 Perform vector addition and scalar multiplication in vector spaces other than <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m>.
			 </li>
		 
			 <li>
				 Describe what it means for a subset of a vector space <m>V</m> to be a <em>subspace</em> of <m>V</m>.
			 	
			 </li>
		 
		 </ul>
	
	 </p>
	 </subsection>
 
	 <subsection xml:id="subsection-4-1-ALO">
		 <title>Advanced Learning Objectives </title>
	<p>
		In addition to mastering the basic objectives, here are the tasks you should be able to perform <em>after class, with practice</em>:
	 
		 <ul>
			 <li>
				 Create subspaces of a given vector space.
		 	
			 </li>
			 <li>
				 Use the definition of subspace to determine if a given subset of a vector space is a subspace.
			 
			 
			 </li>
			 <li>
				 Use Theorem 1 to determine if a given subset of a vector space is a subspace.
				 
			 </li>
		 </ul>
	
	 </p>
	 </subsection>
 
	 <subsection xml:id="subsection-4-1-Resources">
		 <title>Resources</title>
		 
		 
		 <p>
			 <em>Video</em>: First watch the 15 minute 3Blue1Brown video below about the idea of abstract vector spaces. During this video, you will see terms like "eigenvector" and "null space." These are topics we will be learning about later in the course. One significant part of the video uses "basis functions." We will look at basis vectors in Section 4.3 in more detail, but for now, know that a basis is just a set of linearly independent vectors that you can use to create every vector in your space (recall the standard basis vectors <m>\mathbf{e}_i</m> we used). 
		 
			 <video youtube="TgKwz5Ikpc8" end="931"></video>
		 </p>
	 
		 <p>
			 <em>Reading</em>: Read Section 4.1 of the textbook. You do not need to memorize the axioms in the definition on page 192, but you should read through them and think about them in the context of how we have been using <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m> vectors. Examples 4 and 5 are the most relevant in terms of "new" vector spaces. The subspace definition and Theorem 1 are the most significant results of the section.
			 </p>
	 
	 

	
	
	 </subsection>
 
	
	<exercises>
		<p>
			Complete the following exercises in the GP 4-1 file in CoCalc by 8:00 AM on Thursday, 10/8/2020.
		</p>
	
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>
					Give an example of a vector space that is not <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m> for some <m>n</m> or a set of arrows.
				
					

				</p>
			
		
			
			</statement>
		
		</exercise>
	
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>
					Let <m>V</m> be a vector space. Describe what it means for a subset <m>H</m> of <m>V</m> to be a subspace of <m>V</m>.
				
					
				
				</p>
			
		
			
			</statement>
		</exercise>
	
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>
				Let <m>V</m> be the first quadrant in the <m>xy</m>-plane. That is, <m>V=\left\{\begin{bmatrix} x \\ y \end{bmatrix} : x \geq 0, y\geq 0\right\}</m>.
				
				Find a specific vector <m>\mathbf{u}</m> in <m>V</m> and a specific scalar <m>c</m> such that <m>c \mathbf{u}</m> is <em>not</em> in <m>V</m>.
			</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
	
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				What comments or questions do you have about the material? 
			</statement>
		</exercise>
	
	</exercises>	



 
 </section>	 			










 <section xml:id="section-4-2">
	 <title>Guided Practice 4.2: Null Spaces, Column Spaces, and Linear Transformations</title>
 
	 <introduction>
		 <title>Overview</title>
		 <p>
			 The last section defined abstract vector spaces and introduced the idea of <em>subspaces</em>. This section discusses two common ways subspaces arise in applications: 1) as the set of solutions to a homogeneous system of linear equations, and 2) as the span of a collection of vectors. 
	 </p>
	
	 <p>
		 The unifying connection between these two ways is that they can both be related to a matrix, specifically as the <em>null space</em> and <em>column space</em> of a matrix, respectively. After defining these and giving some examples of describing these subspaces for specific matrices, the book compares and contrasts these subspaces, illustrating the important differences between them.
	 </p>

	 <p>
		 The final part of the section defined linear transformations on arbitrary vector spaces (instead of just ones of the form <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m>) and relates the <em>kernel</em> and <em>range</em> of a linear transformation to the null space and column space of a matrix. You can think of kernel and range as more general concepts of the null space and column space. This general perspective is particularly useful when working with linear transformations on spaces other than <m>\mathbb{R}^n</m>.
	 </p>

 
	 </introduction>
 
 
	 <subsection xml:id="subsection-4-2-BLO">
		 <title>Basic Learning Objectives </title>
	<p>
		 You should be able to perform these tasks with reasonable fluency <em>when you arrive to class</em>.
	 
		 <ul>
			 <li>
				 Define the null space and column space of a matrix.
			 
			 </li>
			 <li>
				 Determine if a given vector is in the null space of a given matrix.
			 </li>
		 
			 <li>
				 Find an explicit description of the column space of a matrix.
			 	
			 </li>
		 
		 </ul>
	
	 </p>
	 </subsection>
 
	 <subsection xml:id="subsection-4-2-ALO">
		 <title>Advanced Learning Objectives </title>
	<p>
		In addition to mastering the basic objectives, here are the tasks you should be able to perform <em>after class, with practice</em>:
	 
		 <ul>
			 <li>
				 Find an explicit description of the null space of a matrix.
		 	
			 </li>
			 <li>
				 Determine if a given vector is in the column space of a matrix.
			 
			 </li>
			 <li>
				 Describe the kernel and range of a given linear transformation.
			 </li>
		 </ul>
	
	 </p>
	 </subsection>
 
	 <subsection xml:id="subsection-4-2-Resources">
		 <title>Resources</title>
		 
	 
		 <p>
			 <em>Reading</em>: Read Section 4.2 of the textbook. As you read, try to relate the content to material we have seen and learned before. As has been the case several times, the main "new" material in this section is just viewing stuff we have already done from a new perspective. The table at the top of page 206 is a great summary of the properties and procedures relating to the null space and column space. 
			 </p>
	 
	 

	
	
	 </subsection>
 
	
	<exercises>
		<p>
			Complete the following exercises in the GP 4-2 file in CoCalc by 8:00 AM on Tuesday, 10/13/2020.
		</p>
	
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>
					Determine if <m>\mathbf{w}=\begin{bmatrix} 5 \\ -3 \\ 2\end{bmatrix}</m> is in Nul <m>A</m>, where <m>A = \begin{bmatrix} 5 \amp 21 \amp 19 \\ 13 \amp 23 \amp 2 \\ 8 \amp 14 \amp 1 \end{bmatrix}.</m>
				
					

				</p>
			
		
			
			</statement>
		
		</exercise>
	
	
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				<p>
					Let <m>B = \begin{bmatrix} 2 \amp -6 \\ -1 \amp 3 \\ -4 \amp 12 \\ 3 \amp -9 \end{bmatrix}.</m> Explicitly describe the column space of <m>B</m>. For which value of <m>k</m> is Col <m>B</m> a subspace of <m>\mathbb{R}^k</m>?
			</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
	
		<exercise>
			<statement>
				What comments or questions do you have about the material? 
			</statement>
		</exercise>
	
	</exercises>	



 
 </section>	 			





</chapter>
 
 
 
 

 </book>
</pretext>

